Finding aid to the Caroline Brown Bourland Papers CA.MS.00040
Smith College Archives
Caroline Brown Bourland Papers
1893-1951
Smith College Archives
Bourland, Caroline Brown, 1871-
CA.MS.00040
0.417 linear feet (1 container)
Professor of French and Spanish. Collection contains biographical materials, correspondence, lecture notes, photographs, and publications.
Biographical / Historical
Caroline Brown Bourland was born in Peoria, Illinois on June 4th, 1871. She was an 1893 graduate of Smith College, and continued to study at Bryn Mawr and the Sorbonne, earning her Ph. D. from Bryn Mawr in 1902. Between graduating from college and studying for her doctorate, Caroline Brown Bourland accepted a position teaching English Literature and General History at Pueblo High School in 1893-1894, and another teaching French and Latin at Peoria High School in 1896-1897.
Bourland returned to Smith in 1902, as a professor of French and Spanish. She helped to build the reputation of the Spanish Department, and was instrumental in establishing it as a separate department. In 1913, Bourland switched to teaching Spanish full time, and did so until her retirement in 1939. She hoped that her American students would learn to love Spain as much as she did, and orchestrated an exchange program between Smith and a school in Madrid. Bourland was at least trilingual (not including Latin), and could comfortably read in at least five languages. Caroline Brown Bourland died on February 28, 1956 in Wisconsin.
Scope and Contents
The Caroline Brown Bourland Papers contain biographical materials, correspondence, lecture notes, information on the Hispanic Society of America, article written for the National Encyclopedia, photographs, poetry, publications, tributes and student recommendations spanning her career as a faculty member at Smith College.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Caroline Brown Bourland Papers were donated over a period of time to the Smith College Archives from a variety of sources.
Bourland, Caroline Brown, 1871-; Smith College--Faculty.
- Biographical Material, 1902 - 1940; n. d. (Box 687, Folder 1)
- Correspondence: General, 1921 - 1923 (Box 687, Folder 2)
- Correspondence: William Allan Neilson, 1934 - 1936 (Box 687, Folder 3)
- Correspondence: Personal, 1904 - 1949 (Box 687, Folder 4)
- Diary, 1916 (Box 687, Folder 5)
- Grant - in - Aid, 1938 (Box 687, Folder 6)
- Hispanic Society of America, n. d. (Box 687, Folder 7)
- Lecture Notes, 1931; n. d. (Box 687, Folder 8)
- National Encyclopedia: Correspondence and Articles, 1935 (Box 687, Folder 9)
- Tributes, n. d. (Box 687, Folder 10)
- Photographs, 1893; n. d. (Box 687, Folder 11)
- Poetry, 1895; n. d. (Box 687, Folder 12)
- Publications List, 1928; n. d. (Box 687, Folder 13)
- Publications: Boccaccio and the Decameron and Vida y Hazanas de Juan Belmonte, 1905; 1939 (Box 687, Folder 14)
- Publication: The Short Story in Spain in the Seventeenth Century, 1927 (Box 687, Folder 15)
- Publications: Assorted, 1909 - 1951 (Box 687, Folder 16)
- Retirement, 1939 (Box 687, Folder 17)
- Poetry by Arthur Seelye, 1893; n. d. (Box 687, Folder 18)
- Student Recommendation, 1908; 1916 (Box 687, Folder 19)